Ngũgĩ mss., ca. 1950s-2014 LMC 2905
Lilly Library
- VII. Education
  - New York University (NYU)
    - The Performance of Beauty and Being in Black Aesthetics - Spring, 1998 (Box 40)
    - Roots of Contemporary African Theater - Fall, 1998 (Box 40)
    - Performing History: The Aesthetics of Resistance in the Theater of Black History - Spring, 1999 (Box 40)
    - Postcolonialism and the African Novel - Spring, 1999 (Box 40)
    - Colonialism and the Rise of Modern African Literature - Fall, 1999 (Box 40)
    - The Politics of Performance Space (4 folders) - Fall, 1999 (Box 40)
    - The Politics of Performance Space - Spring, 2001 (Box 40)
    - Postcolonialism and the African Novel - Fall, 2001 (Box 41)
    - Orature: The Roots of Contemporary African Theater - Fall, 2001 (Box 41)
    - Academic calendars (3 folders) (Box 41)
    - Various course materials (3 folders) (Box 41)
  - University of California, Irvine (UCI)
    - Postcolonialism and African Narratives - Winter, 2003 (Box 41)
  - Course Materials
    - Caribbean & African Literature (3 folders) (Box 41)
    - European Literature (5 folders) (Box 41)
    - Afro-American Literature (Box 41)
    - East African Literature (Box 41)
    - African Poetry (Box 42)
    - Okot p'Bitek (Box 42)
    - The Study of Shakespeare's Texts (Box 42)
    - Shakespeare notes (Box 42)
    - The British Council Notes on Literature (multi-volume) (Box 42)
    - Various course materials (28 folders) (Box 42)
    - Student grades and papers (RESTRICTED) (Box 63, Box 64, Box 65, Box 66, Box 67)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Due to the sensitive nature of their contents (including student grades, papers, and IDs), photography and photocopying of materials is prohibited.
  - Writers' Association of Kenya, 1980-1981 (Box 42)
  - Islington Writer in Residence (2 folders), 1985 (Box 42)
- VIII. Conferences
  - African Writers Conference, Makerere College, Kampala, Uganda, June 11-17, 1962 (Box 43)
  - First International Congress of Africanists, Accra, Ghana, December 11-18, 1962 (Box 43)
  - XXXIV International P.E.N. Congress, New York City, program, June 12-18, 1966 (Box 43)
  - African-Scandinavian Writers' Conference, Stockholm, February 6-9, 1967 (Box 43)
  - Second International Congress of Africanists, University of Dakar, Senegal, December 11-20, 1967 (Box 43)
  - UNESCO meeting on The Influence of Colonialism on the Artist… Tanzania, July 5-10, 1971 (Box 43)
  - Linguistic and Cultural Diversity, Ottawa, September 25-30, 1972 (Box 43)
  - Intergovernmental Conference on Cultural Policies in Europe (UNESCO), Final Report, Helsinki, Finland, June 19-28 1972 (Box 43)
  - Permanent Bureau of Afro-Asian Writers, Moscow, June 6-7, 1973 (Box 43)
  - 5th Conference of Afro-Asian Writers, Alma Ata, Kazakhstan U.S.S.R., September 4-9, 1973 (Box 43)
  - Makerere University Conference Papers, 1973-1974 (Box 43)
  - Anti-Imperialist Rally Unite to Fight Racism and Imperialism, Conway Hall, London, April 14, 1974 (Box 43)
  - Conference of Literature Teachers, Nairobi, September 2-4, 1974 (Box 43)
  - UNESCO General Conference Nineteenth Session, Nairobi, 1976 (Box 43)
  - Emergency International Conference on Korea, (2 folders), Tokyo, Japan, August 12-15, 1976 (Box 43)
  - Text and Context in Africa: International Research Methodology in African Literature, Leiden, September 20-24, 1976 (Box 43)
  - FESTAC 77 (2nd World Black and African Festival of Arts and Culture), Lagos, 1977 (Box 43)
    - Documents from organization committee (2 folders), 1974 (Box 43)
    - Conference materials (Box 43)
  - Intercultural Conference on Asia, Africa and Latin America (aaala), Kawasaki, November 4-7, 1981 (Box 43)
  - First International Conference in Solidarity with Grenada, 1981 (Box 43)
  - Education in Zimbabwe: Past Present and Future, Salisbury (Harare), Zimbabwe, August 27, 1981 (Box 43)
  - Second Annual International Conference on African Literature and English Language, University of Calabar, Nigeria, June 15-19, 1982 (Box 43)
  - INTERLIT'82 (International Literature Congress), Köln, Germany, June 18-25, 1982 (Box 43)
  - Conference on Generating Research Tools for African Literatures, London, May 30-31, 1983 (Box 43)
  - 6th Annual Conference on Commonwealth Literature and Language in West Germany, June 16-19, 1983 (Box 43)
  - State and Society in Africa, Mexico, October 23-29, 1983 (Box 44)
  - African Regional Film Workshop, Harare, Zimbabwe, August 27 - September 1, 1984 (Box 44)
  - 40th Edinburgh International Film Festival, August 9-24, 1986 (Box 44)
  - The Challenge of Third World Culture, Duke University, September 25-27, 1986 (Box 44)
  - Artists and Intellectuals Symposium for Child Survival and Development in the Frontline States in Southern Africa, Harare, Zimbabwe, March 1-5, 1988 (Box 44)
  - ICA 88 (Artists Association International International Conference on the Arts), New York, August 25-28, 1988 (Box 44)
  - Europe Seen from the Outside, Berlin, October 7-14, 1988 (Box 44)
  - UNESCO International Meeting on the Protection of the Arts, Madrid, November 7-10, 1988 (Box 44)
  - FESPAC 1988, Dakar, December 15, 1988 - January 15, 1989 (Box 44)
  - Developmental Assistance for the 90s: Adjusting the Perspective, Sweden, April 26-28, 1989 (Box 44)
  - Pan African Writers Association, November 6-14, 1989 (Box 44)
  - First Joint Meeting of the Presidential Council and the General Secretariat Afro-Asian Writers' Association, Cairo, December 4-5, 1989 (Box 44)
  - Writing Together: An International Festival of Writing, Glasglow, 1990 (Box 44)
  - Melbourne Writers' Festival, Melbourne, September 13-17, 1990 (Box 44)
  - International Institute for Human Rights and Democracy in Africa (Inagural Conference), July 5-7, 1991 (Box 44)
  - Pan African Bookfest III, Miami, March 15 - April 21, 1991 (Box 44)
  - Fifth Annual Paul Roberson Festival, Philadelphia, April 1991 (Box 44)
  - Japan and the Third World: Asian and African Writers Conference, Kyoto, Japan, October 31 - November 1, 1992 (Box 44)
  - North-South Counterpoint: Kamau Brathwaite and the Carribean World, New York, October 24, 1992 (Box 44)
  - African Film Festival, New York, April 8, 1993 (Box 44)
  - FEPACI (Pan African Federation of Filmmakers 5th Congress), Ouagadougou, February 21-24, 1993 (Box 44)
  - FESPACO 13, February 20-27, 1993 (Box 44)
    - Conference materials, (3 folders) (Box 44)
    - Conference badge (Box 44)
    - Conference bag (Box 44)
    - Ousmane Sembène film materials (10 folders) (Box 44, Box 45)
  - Black Cinema: A Celebration of Pan-African Film, (2 folders), New York, March 22-30, 1994 (Box 45)
  - 7th Pan-African Conference, Kampala, April 3-8, 1994 (Box 45)
  - Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o: Text and Context, Reading, Pennsylvania, April 7-9, 1994 (Box 45)
  - Symposium on Freedom of Expression, Stavanger, Norway, September 21-23, 1994 (Box 45)
  - LitCon 94, (2 folders), Kuala Lumpur, November 8-10, 1994 (Box 45)
  - National Black Theatre Festival, Winston-Salem, North Carolina, July 31 - August 5, 1995 (Box 45)
  - Screen Griots: Africa and the History of Cinematic Ideas Conference, London, September 9-10, 1995 (Box 45)
  - Carribean Cultural Center/African Diaspora Institute Expressions '95, New York, October - November, 1995 (Box 45)
  - International Seminar on the Nationality Question, Delhi, February 16-19, 1996 (Box 45)
  - World Conference on Linguistic Rights, Barcelona, June 6, 1996 (Box 45)
  - Finding Fanon, NYU, October 11-12, 1996 (Box 45)
  - English Teachers Connect, University of Witwatersrand, July 12-14, 1997 (Box 45)
  - Celebration of the 5th International African Writers' Day (Pan African Writers' Association, PAWA), Accra, Ghana, November 1-7, 1997 (Box 45)
  - African Literature Association 24th Annual Conference (ALA), Austin, Texas, March 25-29, 1998 (Box 45)
  - Against All Odds: African Languages and Literatures into the 21st Century, Asmara, Eritrea, June 15-24, 1999 (Box 45)
  - Mid-America Alliance for African Studies (MAAAS), University of Kansas, September 23-25, 1999 (Box 46)
  - African Studies Association Forty-Second Annual Meeting, Philadelphia, November 11-14, 1999 (Box 46)
  - ACAL 2000: The 31st Annual Conference on African Linguistics, Boston, March 2-5, 2000 (Box 46)
  - Premio Nonino, 2001 (Box 46)
  - African American Studies Department Alumni Reunion and Conference, Yale, May 3-5, 2002 (Box 46)
  - 6th Annual Kimaathi Day Cultural Festival, Orange, New Jersey, June 22, 2002 (Box 46)
  - 28th Annual Meeting of African Literature Association, San Diego, April 3-7, 2002 (Box 46)
  - Ceremony for the Conferment of Honorary Degrees, University of Auckland, July 11, 2005 (Box 46)
  - 10th Time of the Writer International Writers Festival, University of Kwazulu-Natal, March 19-24, 2007 (Box 46)
  - 6th Pan African RFA Conference on Literacy for Community Based Soci-Economic Transformation and Development, Dar es Salaam, April 18, 2009 (Box 46)
  - Second International PKP Scholarly Publishing Conference 2009, Vancouver, July 8-10, 2009 (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous conference materials (2 folders) (Box 46)
- IX. Interviews
  - "James Ngugi" Union News - Alan Marcuson, November 18, 1966 (Box 46)
  - "James Ngugi" Cultural Events in Africa No. 31 - Alan Marcuson, June, 1967 (Box 46)
  - "The End of a Literary Desert Interview with the Kenyan writer James Ngugi in Houston, Texas", April 7, 1971 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o, July 28, 1976 (Box 46)
  - "Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o: The Making of a Rebel" (extract from interview by Dr. Katebalirwe Amooti wa Irumba), January 6 & 11, 1979 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o interviewed by Dr. Katebalirwe Amooti wa Irumba, (4 folders), Limuru, Kenya, January 6 & 11, 1979 (Box 46)
  - Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o - An Autobiographical Interview, March 21, 1979 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o Interview to AFRICA correspondent Magina Magina, ca. 1979 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o Interviewed at Arhus University, December 9, 1980 (Box 46)
  - "Continuing Education African and Carribean Writing: Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o - The River Between", March 13, 1981 (Box 46)
  - "Marxism Today" Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o - Kenneth Parker, September, 1982 (Box 46)
  - "An Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o" - Jane Wilkinson (extracts from interviews), 1983-1984 (Box 46)
  - Interview with Feroza Jussawalla and Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o, ca. 1986 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o Interviewed by UFAHAMU African Studies Center UCLA Washington, D.C., November 10, 1990 (Box 46)
  - Five College Ink Vol. 4 Fall '91 (excerpt from Nadine Gordimer and Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o interview), October 9, 1981 (Box 46)
  - College Students Question Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o: Excerpts from a Class (Penn State University), January 23, 1992 (Box 46)
  - I Will Marry When I Want: A Highschool Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o - Tami Alpert, 1992 (Box 46)
  - Take 1: Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o Interviewed by Charles Cantalupo, January 23, 1993 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ - FESPACO '93, February, 1993 (Box 46)
  - Ngũgĩ Interview - Thomas Bikales, April 27, 1993 (Box 46)
  - "Penpoints, Gunpoints, and Dreams: An Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o" - Charles Cantulopo, November 11, 1998 (Box 46)
  - "From The Garden of Languages, the Nectar of Art: An Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o" - Uzoma Esonwanne, 2006 (Box 46)
  - "James Ngugi talks to Peter Darling", undated (Box 46)
  - Interviews about Maitũ Njugĩra (Mother, Sing for Me), undated (Box 46)
  - "An Interview with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o", Göteborg, Sweden - J.B., undated (Box 46)
  - "Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o" - Lee Nichols, undated (Box 46)
  - Unidentified interviews with Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o (4 folders) (Box 46)
- X. Theatre
  - Afrika Cultural Centre, 1981-1984 (Box 47)
  - Agbo Rago (program) performed by Jelili Atiku, September 27, 2009 (Box 47)
  - The Black Hermit (Box 47)
    - The Black Hermit & Sons and Daughters, presented by The National Theatre Company at the Kenya Culturral Center, program, February, 1970 (Box 47)
    - The Black Hermit, presented by the African Arts theater Company, November 6-22, 1992 (Box 47)
  - Café Teater Copenhagen, 1980-1981 (Box 47)
  - Chikwakwa Theatre, University of Zambia, 1972-1973 (Box 47)
  - Community Theatre Workshop (Zimbabwe), July 6-8, 1983 (Box 47)
  - Edufa presented by The Oak Theatre, University of Nigeria, program, 1981 (Box 47)
  - Free Traveling Theatre - correspondence with the Sweedish Institute, April 2, 1975 - April 14, 1975 (Box 47)
  - Game of Silence, Kenya National Theatre, program, May 12-17, 1977 (Box 47)
  - Ghana Dance Ensemble, The National Dance Company, program (Box 47)
  - Ghosts, presented by National Theatre Company at Kenya Cultural Centre, program, January 30 - February 6, 1975 (Box 47)
  - I Will Marry When I Want (Box 47)
    - I Will Marry When I Want, presented by Department of Theatre Arts University of Benin, program, 1985 (Box 47)
    - I Will Marry When I Want (to the Editor of the Herald), 1986 (Box 47)
  - International Theatre Institute, 1980-1981 (Box 47)
  - Kamiriithu Community Education & Cultural Centre, 1977-1982 (Box 47)
  - Kenya Cultural Centre, 1962-1977 (Box 47)
  - The Kenya National Theatre holiday card (Box 47)
  - The Kenya Schools National Drama Festical The Festival to End All Debates - Wanjiku Matenjwa (Box 47)
  - Proposed Policy Guide for the Development of Theatre and Drama in Kenya - Dr. Kimani and Alex Gichuke (Box 47)
  - Mwangaza Centre The Performing and Creative Arts Centre, Kenyatta University College, Nairobi, Kenya, May 10, 1979 (Box 47)
  - Nairobi University Free Traveling Theatre, 1976-1977 (Box 47)
  - The Nigerian National Arts Theatre & Stage (plan) (Box 47)
  - The Palm-Wine Drinkard (program) Ogunmola Traveling Theatre (Box 47)
  - PETA-CITASA Theater Arts Workshop (Philippine Educational Theater Association) (Box 47)
  - Theatre in a Changing World University of Dar Es Salaam Inagural Lecture Series No.3 - Herbert L. Shore, April, 1969 (Box 47)
  - Theories of Dance in Nigeria - Onuora Ossie Enekwe, 1991 (Box 47)
  - Towards a Truly African Theartre Seminars (program) organized by Theatre Arts Department, University of Dar Es Salaam, Tanzania, August 28 - September 5, 1969 (Box 47)
  - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi (Box 47)
    - Stage directions, undated (Box 47)
    - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi presented by Kenya FESTAC '77 Drama Group (2 folders), 1976-1977 (Box 47)
    - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi presented by the Wazalendo Players '84 (3 folders), 1984 (Box 47)
    - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi (program) presented by Department of Speech and Drama, University od Durban-Westville, June 3-8, 1985 (Box 47)
    - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi (program) presented by University of Nigeria, 1992 (Box 47)
    - The Trial of Dedan Kimathi (program) presented by Zimbabwe Peoples Theatre Project, undated (Box 47)
    - Dedan Kimathi by Kenneth Watene (comments/review by Ngũgĩ) undated (Box 47)
  - UAPA News (Union of African Performing Artists) No.3, Zimbabwe, October, 1984 (Box 47)
- XI. Film
  - Dreams in a Riot of Color John Matshikiza (Box 47)
  - Film in Africa, 1981-1989 (Box 47)
  - Film Studies (Box 47)
  - Journey Across Three Continents: Film and Lecture Series, 1985 (Box 47)
  - Modern Days Ancient Nights: Thirty Years of African Filmmaking, April 17 - May 23, 1993 (Box 47)
  - White Michief (Box 47)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 47)
- XII. Subject Files
  - Abdilalif Abdalla (2 folders) (Box 47)
  - African World Press, galley proofs (Box 47)
  - Bamanankan Language Dictionary (Box 47)
  - Brockman Inc. (Box 47)
  - Frank M. Chipasula (Box 48)
  - Dan Baron Cohen (Box 48)
  - Dhaagicw Glossaries (Box 48)
  - Shiraz Durrani (3 folders) (Box 48)
  - Drum Short Story Competition (Box 48)
  - Gitahi Gititi (2 folders) (Box 48)
  - Kenya (Box 48)
    - African Socialism and its Application to Planning in Kenya [Republic of Kenya], 1965 (Box 48)
    - The Constitiution of the Republic of Kenya, 1967 (Box 48)
    - Economy/Industry (Box 48)
    - Education (Box 48)
    - Electorial Commission, 1992-1993 (Box 48)
    - General Elections, 1982-1983 (Box 48)
    - Daniel arap Moi (Box 48)
    - Kenya Before Independence, 1957-1963 (Box 48)
    - Kenya Council for Cultural Renewal (Box 48)
    - Kenya Literature Bureau Bill, 1980 (Box 48)
    - Kenya National Culture Festival (Box 48)
    - The Law Society of Kenya's Memorandum on the Proposed Court Appeal for Kenya, 1977 (Box 48)
    - National Christian Council of Kenya Southen Africa Committee (Box 48)
    - Rũthanjũ (Box 48)
    - Wagalla Massacres (Box 48)
  - John La Rose (Box 48)
  - Waithira Mbuthia (2 folders) (Box 48)
  - Nation Newspaper (Box 48)
  - Neustadt International Prize for Literature (Box 48)
  - Thiong'o Ngũgĩ (Box 48)
  - Sonia Sanchez (Box 49)
  - Carol Sicherman (2 folders) (Box 49)
  - James G. Spady (Box 49)
  - The Sweedish Institute (Box 49)
  - Edwin Waiyaki (Box 49)
- XIII. Travel (Box 49)
- XIV. Ephemera (Box 49)
  - Calendars (Box 49)
  - Flyers (Box 49)
  - Drawings (2 folders) (Box 49)
  - Kwanza Award (Box 49)
  - Nametags (Box 49)
  - Penpoints Gunpoints and Dreams (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Box 49)
- XV. Photos (Box 50, Box 51, Box 77)
- XVI. Personal/Family (Box 51)
- XVII. Clippings (Box 51, Box 52)
- XVIII. Research (Box 52, Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box 57)
- XIX. Printed Material (Box 57, Box 58, Box 59, Box 60, Box 74)
- XX. Legal (Box 61)
- XXI. Financial (Box 61, Box 62)
- XXII. Address books/notebooks/messages (Box 68)
- XXIII. Notebooks (Box 69)
- XXIV. Audio Visual and Born Digital (Box 70, Box 71, Box 72, Box 73)
- XXV. Awards, Certificates, Degrees
  - Lotus Prize for Literature, 1973 (Box 74)
  - Albright College, Doctor of Humane Letters, 1994 (Box 74)
  - Roskilde University, Honorary Doctorate in Philosophy, 1997 (Box 74)
  - Medal of the Presidency of the Italian Cabinet Awarded by the International Scientific Committee of the Pio Manzu Centre, Rimini, Italy, 2002 (Box 74)
  - Grinzane Cavour Literary Prize for African Literature, 2008 (Box 74)
  - NYU, Honorary Degree of Doctor of Letters, 2008 (Box 74)
  - University of Dar es Salaam, Honorary Doctorate in Literature, 2013 (Box 74)
- XXVI. Posters, Broadsides (Box 76)
- XXVII. Miscellaneous
  - Plastic Clock (Box 74)
  - Video camera and hat (Box 78 (Oversize))
  - Leather satchel (Box 79 (Oversize))